<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<docbook:article xmlns:docbook="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook docbook.xsd">
	<docbook:info>
		<docbook:title>From The Editor's Desk</docbook:title>
		<docbook:author>
			<docbook:personname>Philip Nelson</docbook:personname>
		</docbook:author>
	</docbook:info>
	<docbook:para>
		Welcome to the new look IDUG Solutions Journal, developed in response to your feedback received
		over the last few months.      
	</docbook:para>
	<docbook:para>
		Our main feature article this month is a case study in producing and consuming documents in ODF 
		(Open Document Format), as used by the free OpenOffice.org suite, using DB2 pureXML.   The techniques
		described in this article could be readily applied to a wide variety of other use cases.   
	</docbook:para>
	<docbook:para>
		We are also pleased to have a full complement of columns from our regular contributors.   Roger Miller
		talks about the choices to be made when considering a DB2 for z/OS upgrade.   John Hornibrook discusses
		how to guard against queries going bad.   And Craig Mullins looks at the relationship which needs to be
		built between DBAs and Storage Managers.   Next time we hope to add to our stable of regular columnists
		so watch this space.    
	</docbook:para>
	<docbook:para>
		As I said before this is the first issue of a new look ISJ.   It is still very much a work in progress
		as we learn a bunch of new tools.   This first issue is not exactly a "thing of beauty" but we hope
		this will get better as our skills build.   At least I believe there is plenty of good technical
		content in it.
	</docbook:para>
	<docbook:para>
		We are urgently in need of volunteers to help with the ISJ.   These fall into three categories -
		<docbook:orderedlist>
			<docbook:listitem>
				First and foremost we need authors.   We'd be delighted to hear from anyone who would be 
				willing to spend time working on a technical article for the magazine.
			</docbook:listitem>
			<docbook:listitem>
				We also need reviewers to join the ERB (Editorial Review Board).  Reviewers can be of two
				types : technical and grammatical.   If you think you could contribute in either of these
				areas then please drop me a line.   You don't need to be a cross-platform DB2 expert to
				be a good technical reviewer : indeed when I started with ISJ I learnt a lot as I checked
				the technical correctness of articles against the publicly available documentation.
			</docbook:listitem>
			<docbook:listitem>
				Finally we need folks to help with the preparation of the content.   If anyone out there has
				experience using the DocBook standard (or would be willing to learn) then we would be delighted
				to hear from you.   Our aim is to turn the ISJ back into a publication not only with the best
				quality of content, but which also looks professional.   
			</docbook:listitem>
		</docbook:orderedlist>
	</docbook:para>
	<docbook:para>
		We hope to have the next issue of the ISJ available before the end of the year.   Until then ...
	</docbook:para>
	<docbook:para>
		... don't just do it, DB2 it !!!
	</docbook:para>
	<docbook:para>
		Phil Nelson (ISJ Executive Editor)
	</docbook:para>
</docbook:article>
